<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2018 Joel Feldman, Andrew Rechnitzer and Elyse Yeager -->
<!-- This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License-->
<!-- https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0 -->
<exercises><title>Exercises for <sect/><nbsp/><xref ref="ssec_pop"/> </title>

<exercisegroup><title><conceptual/></title>
<introduction></introduction>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
Let a population at time <m>t</m> be given by the Malthusian model,
<me>
P(t)=P(0)e^{bt}\mbox{ for some positive constant } b.</me>
</p>

<p>Evaluate <m>\ds\lim_{t \to \infty}P(t)</m>. Does this model make sense for large values of <m>t</m>?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
<m>P(0)</m> is also (probably) a positive constant.
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
If <m>P(0)=0</m>, yes. If <m>P(0) \neq 0</m>,
no: it does not take into account external constraints on population growth.
</p></answer>
<solution><p>
Since <m>b</m> is a positive constant, <m>\ds\lim_{t \to \infty}e^{bt}=\infty</m>. Therefore:
<md>
<mrow>
\lim_{t \to \infty}P(t)&amp;=\lim_{t \to \infty} P(0)e^{bt}
=\left\{\begin{array}{cc}
0&amp;\mbox{ if }P(0)=0
</mrow><mrow>
\infty&amp;\mbox{ if }P(0) \gt 0
\end{array}\right.
</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>If <m>P(0)=0</m>, then the model simply says <q>a population that starts with no individuals continues to have no individuals indefinitely,</q> which certainly makes sense. If <m>P(0) \neq 0</m>, then (since we can't have a negative population) <m>P(0) \gt 0</m>, and the model says <q>a population that starts out with some individuals will end up with any gigantically huge number you can think of, given enough time.</q> This one doesn't make so much sense. Populations only grow to a certain finite amount, due to scarcity of resources and such. In the derivation of the Malthusian model, we assume a constant net birth rate--that the birth and death rates (per individual) don't depend on the population, which is not a reasonable assumption long-term.
</p></solution>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><title><procedural/></title>
<introduction></introduction>

<exercise purpose="RQS">
<statement><p>
In the 1950s, pure-bred wood bison were thought to be extinct. However, a small population was found in Canada. For decades, a captive breeding program has been working to increase their numbers, and from time to time wood bison are released to the wild. Suppose in 2015, a released herd numbered 121 animals, and a year later, there were 136
<fn>These numbers are loosely based on animals actually released near Shageluk, Alaska in 2015. Watch the first batch being released <url href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GqRHe769AQM">here</url>.</fn>.
If the wood bison adhere to the Malthusian model (a big assumption!), and if there are no more releases of captive animals, how many animals will the herd have in 2020?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
The assumption that the animals grow according to the Malthusian model tells us that their population  <m>t</m> years after 2015 is given by
<m>P(t)=121e^{bt}</m> for some constant <m>b</m>.
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
The Malthusian model predicts the herd will number 217
            individuals in 2020.
            </p></answer>
<solution><p>
The assumption that the animals grow according to the Malthusian model tells us that their population  <m>t</m> years after 2015 is given by
<m>P(t)=121e^{bt}</m> for some constant <m>b</m>, since <m>121=P(0)</m>, the population 0 years after 2015. The information about 2016 tells us
<md>
<mrow>
136=P(1)&amp;=121e^{b}
</mrow><mrow>
\frac{136}{121}&amp;=e^b
</mrow>
<intertext>This gives us a better idea of <m>P(t)</m>:</intertext><mrow>
P(t)&amp;=121e^{bt}=121\left(\frac{136}{121}\right)^t
</mrow>
<intertext>2020 is 5 years after 2015, so in 2020 (assuming the population keeps growing according to the Malthusian model) the population will be</intertext><mrow>
P(5)&amp;=121\left(\frac{136}{121}\right)^5\approx217
</mrow>
</md>
In 2020, the Malthusian model predicts the herd will number 217 individuals.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
A founding colony of 1,000 bacteria is placed in a petri dish of yummy bacteria food. After an hour, the population has doubled. Assuming the Malthusian model, how long will it take for the colony to triple its original population?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
The Malthusian model says that the population of bacteria <m>t</m> hours after being placed in the dish will be <m>P(t)=1000e^{bt}</m> for some constant <m>b</m>.
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
<m>\dfrac{\log(3)}{\log(2)}\approx 1.6</m> hours
</p></answer>
<solution><p>
Since the initial population of bacteria is 1000 individuals, the Malthusian model says that the population of bacteria <m>t</m> hours after being placed in the dish will be <m>P(t)=1000e^{bt}</m> for some constant <m>b</m>. Since <m>P(1)=2000</m>,
<md>
<mrow>
2000=P(1)&amp;=1000e^{b}
</mrow><mrow>
2&amp;=e^b
</mrow>
<intertext>So, the population at time <m>t</m> is</intertext><mrow>
P(t)&amp;=1000\cdot 2^t
</mrow>
<intertext>We want to know at what time the population triples, to 3,000 individuals.</intertext><mrow>
3000&amp;=1000\cdot 2^t
</mrow><mrow>
3&amp;=2^t
</mrow><mrow>
\log(3)&amp;=\log\left(2^t\right)=t\log(2)
</mrow><mrow>
t&amp;=\frac{\log(3)}{\log(2)}\approx 1.6
</mrow>
</md>
The population triples in about 1.6 hours. Note that the tripling time depends only on the constant <m>b</m>. In particular, it does not depend on the initial condition <m>P(0)</m>.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise purpose="RQS">
<statement><p>
A single pair of  rats comes to an island after a shipwreck. They multiply according to the Malthusian model. In 1928, there were 1,000 rats on the island, and the next year there were 1500. When was the shipwreck?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
If 1928 is <m>a</m> years after the shipwreck, you might want to make use of the fact that <m>e^{b(a+1)}=e^{ba}e^b</m>.
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
1912 or 1913
</p></answer>
<solution><p>
According to the Malthusian Model, if the ship wrecked at year <m>t=0</m> and 2 rats washed up on the island, then <m>t</m> years after the wreck, the population of rats will be
<md>
<mrow>
P(t)&amp;=2e^{bt}
</mrow>
<intertext>for some constant <m>b</m>. We want to get rid of this extraneous variable <m>b</m>, so we use the given information. If 1928 is <m>a</m> years after the wreck:</intertext><mrow>
1000=P(a)&amp;=2e^{ba}
</mrow><mrow>
1500=P(a+1)&amp;=2e^{b(a+1)}=2e^{ba}e^b
</mrow>
<intertext>So,</intertext><mrow>
(1000)\left(e^b\right)&amp;=\left(2e^{ba}\right)\left(e^b\right)=1500
</mrow>
<intertext>Which tells us</intertext><mrow>
e^b&amp;=\frac{1500}{1000}=1.5
</mrow>
<intertext>Now, our model is complete:</intertext><mrow>
P(t)&amp;=2\left(e^b\right)^t=2\cdot1.5^t
</mrow>
<intertext>Since <m>P(a)=1000</m>, we can find <m>a</m>:</intertext><mrow>
1000=P(a)&amp;=2\cdot1.5^a
</mrow><mrow>
500&amp;=1.5^a
</mrow><mrow>
\log(500)&amp;=\log\left(1.5^a\right)=a\log(1.5)
</mrow><mrow>
a&amp;=\frac{\log(500)}{\log(1.5)}\approx 15.3
</mrow>
</md>
So, the year 1928 was about 15.3 years after the shipwreck. Since we aren't given a month when the rats reached exactly 1000 in number, that puts the shipwreck at the year 1912 or 1913.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
A farmer wants to farm cochineals, which are insects used to make red dye. The farmer raises a small number of cochineals as a test. In three months, a test population of cochineals will increase from 200 individuals to 1000, given ample space and food.
</p>

<p>The farmer's plan is to start with an initial population of <m>P(0)</m> cochineals,
and after a year have <m>1\,000\,000+P(0)</m> cochineals, so that one million can be harvested, and <m>P(0)</m> saved to start breeding again. What initial population <m>P(0)</m> does the Malthusian model suggest?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
If the population has a net birthrate per individual per unit time of <m>b</m>, then the Malthusian model predicts that the number of individuals at time <m>t</m> will be
<m>P(t)=P(0)e^{bt}</m>. You can use the test population to find <m>e^b</m>.
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
<m>\dfrac{10^6}{5^4-1}\approx 1603</m>
</p></answer>
<solution><p>
The Malthusian model suggests that, if we start with <m>P(0)</m> cochineals, their population after 3 months will be
<md>
<mrow>
P(t)&amp;=P(0)e^{bt}
</mrow>
<intertext>for some constant <m>b</m>. The constant <m>b</m> is the net birthrate per population member per unit time. Assuming that the net birthrate for a larger population will be the same as the test population, we can use the data from the test to find <m>e^b</m>. Let <m>Q(t)</m> be the number of individuals in the test population at time <m>t</m>.</intertext><mrow>
Q(t)&amp;=Q(0)e^{bt}=200e^{bt}
</mrow><mrow>
1000&amp;=Q(3)=200e^{3b}
</mrow><mrow>
5&amp;=e^{3b}
</mrow><mrow>
e^b&amp;=5^{1/3}
</mrow>
<intertext>Now that we have an idea of the birthrate, we predict</intertext><mrow>
P(t)&amp;=P(0)\left(e^{b}\right)^t=P(0)\cdot5^{\tfrac{t}{3}}
</mrow>
<intertext>We want <m>P(12)=10^6+P(0)</m>.</intertext><mrow>
10^6+P(0)=P(12)&amp;=P(0)\cdot 5^{\tfrac{12}{3}}=P(0)\cdot 5^4
</mrow><mrow>
10^6&amp;=P(0)\cdot 5^4-P(0)=P(0)\left[5^4-1\right]
</mrow><mrow>
P(0)&amp;=\frac{10^6}{5^4-1}\approx 1603
</mrow>
</md>
The farmer should use an initial population of (at least) about 1603 individuals.
</p>

<p>Remark: if we hadn't specified that we need to save <m>P(0)</m> individuals to start next year's population, the number of individual cochineals we would want to start with to get a million in a year would be 1600--almost the same!
</p></solution>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><title><application/></title>
<introduction></introduction>

<exercise purpose="RQS">
<statement><p>
Let <m>f(t)=100e^{kt}</m>, for some constant <m>k</m>.
<ol label="a">
<li> If <m>f(t)</m> is the amount of a decaying radioactive isotope in a sample at time <m>t</m>,
what is the amount of the isotope in the sample when <m>t=0</m>? What is the sign of <m>k</m>?
</li>
<li> If <m>f(t)</m> is the number of individuals in a population that is growing according to the Malthusian model, how many individuals are there when <m>t=0</m>? What is the sign of <m>k</m>?
</li>
<li> If <m>f(t)</m> is the temperature of an object at time <m>t</m>, given by Newton's Law of Cooling, what is the ambient temperature surrounding the object? What is the sign of <m>k</m>?
</li>
</ol>
</p></statement>
<hint><p>
One way to investigate the sign of <m>k</m> is to think about <m>f'(t)</m>: is it positive or negative?
</p></hint>
<answer><p>
(a) At <m>t=0</m>, there are 100 units of the radioactive isotope in the sample. <m>k</m> is negative.
</p>
<p>
(b) At <m>t=0</m>, there are 100 individuals in the population. <m>k</m> is positive.
</p>
<p>
(c) The ambient temperature is 0 degrees. <m>k</m> is negative.
</p></answer>
<solution><p>
<ul>
<li>[(a)] Since <m>f(t)</m> gives the amount of  the radioactive isotope in the sample at time <m>t</m>, the amount of the radioactive isotope in the sample when <m>t=0</m> is <m>f(0)=100e^0=100</m> units. Since the sample is decaying,  <m>f(t)</m> is decreasing, so <m>f'(t)</m> is negative. Differentiating, <m>f'(t)=k(100e^{kt})</m>. Since <m>100e^{kt}</m> is positive and <m>f'(t)</m> is negative, <m>k</m> is negative.
</li>
<li>[(b)] Since <m>f(t)</m> gives the size of the population at time <m>t</m>, the number of individuals in the population when <m>t=0</m> is <m>f(0)=100e^0=100</m>. Since the population is growing,  <m>f(t)</m> is increasing, so <m>f'(t)</m> is positive. Differentiating, <m>f'(t)=k(100e^{kt})</m>. Since <m>100e^{kt}</m> is positive and <m>f'(t)</m> is positive, <m>k</m> is also positive.
</li>
<li>[(c)] Newton's Law of Cooling gives the temperature of an object at time <m>t</m> as
<m>f(t)=[f(0)-A]e^{kt}+A</m>, where <m>A</m> is the ambient temperature surrounding the object. In our case, the ambient temperature is 0 degrees. In an object whose temperature is being modelled by Newton's Law of Cooling,  it doesn't matter whether the object is heating or cooling, <m>k</m> is negative. We saw this in Question<nbsp/><xref ref="s3_3_2Knegative"/> of Section<nbsp/><xref ref="sec_newtonCooling"/>,
 but it bears repeating. Since <m>f(t)</m> approaches the ambient temperature (in this case, 0) as <m>t</m> goes to infinty:
<me>
\lim_{t \to \infty}100e^{kt}=0</me>
so <m>k</m> is negative.
</li>
</ul>
</p></solution>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>

</exercises>
