<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2018 Joel Feldman, Andrew Rechnitzer and Elyse Yeager -->
<!-- This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License-->
<!-- https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0 -->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec_mvt">
<title>The Mean Value Theorem</title>
<introduction>

<p>Consider the following situation. Two towns are separated by a 120km long stretch of road.
The police in town <m>A</m> observe a car leaving at 1pm. Their colleagues in town <m>B</m> see the
car arriving at 2pm. After a quick phone call between the two police stations, the driver
is issued a fine for going <m>120km/h</m> at some time between 1pm and 2pm. It is intuitively
obvious
<fn>Unfortunately there are many obvious things that are decidedly false <mdash/>
for example <q>There are more rational numbers than integers.</q> or <q>Viking helmets had
horns on them</q>.</fn>
 that, because his average velocity was <m>120km/h</m>, the driver
must have been going at least <m>120km/h</m> at some point. From a knowledge of the
average velocity of the car, we are able to deduce something about an
instantaneous velocity
<fn>
Recall that speed and velocity are not the same. Velocity specifies the direction of motion as well as the rate of
change. Objects moving along a straight line have velocities that are positive
or negative numbers indicating  which direction the object is moving along the
line. Speed, on the other hand, is the distance travelled per unit time and is
always a non-negative number <mdash/> it is the absolute value of velocity.
</fn>
.
</p>

<p>Let us turn this around a little bit. Consider the premise of a 90s action
film
<fn>The sequel won a Raspberry award for <q>Worst remake or sequel</q>.</fn>
 <mdash/> a
bus must travel at a velocity of no less than <m>80km/h</m>. Being a bus, it is unable to go
faster than, say, <m>120km/h</m>. The film runs for about 2 hours, and lets assume that there
is about thirty minutes of non-action <mdash/> so the bus' velocity is constrained between
<m>80</m> and <m>120km/h</m> for a total of <m>1.5</m> hours.
</p>

<p>It is again obvious that the bus must have travelled between <m>80 \times 1.5 = 120</m> and
<m>120\times 1.5 = 180km</m> during the film. This time, from a knowledge of the instantaneous
rate of change of position <mdash/> the derivative <mdash/> throughout a 90 minute time
interval, we are able to say something about the net change of position during the 90
minutes.
</p>

<p>In both of these scenarios we are making use of a piece of mathematics called the Mean
Value Theorem. It says that, under appropriate hypotheses, the average rate of change
<m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m> of a function over an interval is achieved exactly by the
instantaneous rate of change <m>f'(c)</m> of the function at some
<fn>There must be at
least one such point <mdash/> there could be more than one <mdash/> but there cannot be zero.</fn>
(unknown) point <m>a\le c\le b</m>. We shall get to a precise statement in
Theorem<nbsp/><xref ref="thm_DIFFmvt"/>. We start working up to it by first considering the special case
in which <m>f(a)=f(b)</m>.
</p>
</introduction>
<subsection>
<title>Rolle's Theorem</title>

<theorem xml:id="thm_DIFFrolle"><title>Rolle's theorem</title>
<statement><p>
Let <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> be real numbers with <m>a \lt b</m>. And let <m>f</m> be a function so that
<ul>
<li> <m>f(x)</m> is continuous on the closed interval <m>a\le x\le b</m>,
</li>
<li> <m>f(x)</m> is differentiable on the open interval <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>, and
</li>
<li> <m>f(a)=f(b)</m>
</li>
</ul>
then there is a <m>c</m> strictly between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, i.e. obeying <m>a \lt c \lt b</m>, such that
<md>
<mrow>
f'(c)=0.
</mrow>
</md>
</p></statement>
</theorem>

<p>Again, like the two scenarios above, this theorem says something intuitively obvious.
Consider <mdash/> if you throw a ball straight up into the air and then catch it, at some time
in between the throw and the catch it must be stationary. Translating this into
mathematical statements, let <m>s(t)</m> be the height of the ball above the ground in metres,
and let <m>t</m> be time from the moment the ball is thrown in seconds. Then we have
<md>
<mrow>
  s(0) &amp;= 1 &amp; \text{we release the ball at about hip-height}
</mrow><mrow>
  s(4) &amp;= 1 &amp; \text{we catch the ball $4s$ later at hip-height}
</mrow>
</md>
Then we know there is some time in between <mdash/> say at <m>t=c</m> <mdash/> when the ball is
stationary (in this case when the ball is at the top of its trajectory). I.e.
<md>
<mrow>
  v(c) = s'(c) &amp;= 0.
</mrow>
</md>
Rolle's theorem guarantees that for any differentiable function that starts and ends at
the same value, there will always be at least one point between the start and finish
where the derivative is zero.</p>

<sidebyside width="90%">
<image source="text/figs/rolle"/>
</sidebyside>

<p>There can, of course, also be multiple points at which the derivative is zero <mdash/> but
there must always be at least one. Notice, however, the theorem
<fn>Notice this is
very similar to the intermediate value theorem (see Theorem<nbsp/><xref ref="thm_ivt"/>)</fn>
</p>

<p>does not tell us the value of <m>c</m>, just that such a <m>c</m> must exist.
</p>

<example><title>A simple application of Rolle's theorem</title>
<p>
We can use Rolle's theorem to show that the function
<md>
<mrow>
  f(x) &amp;= \sin(x)-\cos(x)
</mrow>
</md>
has a point <m>c</m> between <m>0</m> and <m>\frac{3\pi}{2}</m> so that <m>f'(c)=0</m>.
</p>

<p>To apply Rolle's theorem we first have to show the function satisfies the conditions of
the theorem on the interval <m>[0,\frac{3\pi}{2}]</m>.
<ul>
<li> Since <m>f</m> is the sum of sine and cosine it is continuous on the interval and also
differentiable on the interval.
</li>
<li> Further, since
<md>
<mrow>
  f(0) &amp;= \sin 0 - \cos 0 = 0-1 = -1
</mrow><mrow>
  f\left(\frac{3\pi}{2}\right) &amp;= \sin\frac{3\pi}{2} - \cos\frac{3\pi}{2} = -1-0 = -1
</mrow>
</md>
  we can now apply Rolle's theorem.
</li>
<li> Rolle's theorem implies that there must be a point <m>c \in (0,3\pi/2)</m> so that
<m>f'(c) =0</m>.
</li>
</ul>
While Rolle's theorem doesn't tell us the value of <m>c</m>, this example is sufficiently
simple that we can find it directly.
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(x) &amp;= \cos x + \sin x
</mrow><mrow>
  f'(c) &amp;= \cos c + \sin c  =  0 &amp; \text{rearrange}
</mrow><mrow>
  \sin c&amp;= - \cos c &amp; \text{and divide by $\cos c$}
</mrow><mrow>
  \tan c &amp;= -1
</mrow>
</md>
Hence <m>c = \frac{3\pi}{4}</m>. We have sketched the function and the relevant points below.</p>

<sidebyside width="40%">
<image source="text/figs/rolle_sketch"/>
</sidebyside>
</example>

<p>A more substantial application of Rolle's theorem (in conjunction with the intermediate
value theorem <mdash/> Theorem<nbsp/><xref ref="thm_ivt"/>) is to show that a function does not have
multiple zeros in an interval:</p>

<example><title>Showing an equation has exactly 1 solution</title>
<p>
Show that the equation <m>2x-1=\sin(x)</m> has exactly 1 solution.
<ul>
<li><p> Start with a rough sketch of each side of the equation</p>

<sidebyside width="75%">
<image source="text/figs/rolle_sketch2"/>
</sidebyside>

<p> This seems like it should be true.</p>
</li>
<li> Notice that the problem we are trying to solve is equivalent to showing
that the function
<md>
<mrow>
  f(x) &amp;= 2x-1-\sin(x)
</mrow>
</md>
has only a single zero.
</li>
<li> Since <m>f(x)</m> is the sum of a polynomial and a sine function, it is continuous and
differentiable everywhere. Thus we can apply both the IVT and Rolle's theorem.
</li>
<li> Notice that <m>f(0)=-1</m> and <m>f(2) = 4-1-\sin(2) = 3-\sin(2) \geq 2</m>, since <m>-1\leq
\sin(2) \leq 1</m>. Thus by the IVT we know there is at least one number <m>c</m> between <m>0</m> and
<m>2</m> so that <m>f(c)=0</m>.
</li>
<li> But our job is only half done <mdash/> this shows that there is at least one zero, but
it does not tell us there is no more than one. We have more work to do, and Rolle's
theorem is the tool we need.
</li>
<li><p> Consider what would happen if <m>f(x)</m> is zero in 2 places <mdash/> that is, there are
numbers <m>a,b</m> so that <m>f(a)=f(b)=0</m>.
<ul>
<li> Since <m>f(x)</m> is differentiable everywhere and <m>f(a)=f(b)=0</m>, we can apply Rolle's
theorem.
</li>
<li> Hence we know there is a point <m>c</m> between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> so that <m>f'(c)=0</m>.
</li>
<li> But let us examine <m>f'(x)</m>:
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(x) &amp;= 2- \cos x
</mrow>
</md>
Since <m>-1\leq \cos x \leq 1</m>, we must have that <m>f'(x) \geq 1</m>.
</li>
<li> But this contradicts Rolle's theorem which tells us there must be a point at which
the derivative is zero.
</li>
</ul>
Thus the function cannot be zero at two different places <mdash/> otherwise we'd have a
contradiction.</p>
</li>
</ul>
We can actually nail down the value of <m>c</m> using the bisection approach we used in
example<nbsp/><xref ref="eg_bisection"/>. If we do this carefully we find that <m>c \approx
0.887862\dots</m>
</p>

</example>

</subsection>
<subsection><title>Back to the MVT</title>
<p>Rolle's theorem can be generalised in a straight-forward way; given a differentiable
function <m>f(x)</m> we can still say something about <m>\diff{f}{x}</m>, even if <m>f(a) \neq f(b)</m>. Consider the following sketch:</p>

<figure xml:id="fig_rolle_to_mvt">
 <caption/>
 <image width="75%" source="text/figs/rolle_to_mvt"/>
</figure>

<p>All we have done is tilt the picture so that <m>f(a)  \lt  f (b)</m>. Now we can no longer
guarantee that there will be a point on the graph where the tangent line is horizontal,
but there will be a point where the tangent line is parallel to the secant joining <m>(a,
f(a))</m> to <m>(b, f(b))</m>.
</p>

<p>To state this in terms of our first scenario back at the beginning of this section,
suppose that you are driving along the <m>x</m><ndash/>axis. At time <m>t=a</m> you are at <m>x=f(a)</m> and at
time <m>t=b</m> you are at <m>x=f(b)</m>. For simplicity, let's suppose that <m>b \gt a</m> and <m>f(b)\ge
f(a)</m>, just like in the above sketch.  Then during the time interval in question you
travelled a net distance of <m>f(b)-f(a)</m>. It took you <m>b-a</m> units
of time to travel that distance, so your average velocity was
<m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>. You may very well have been going faster than
 <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m> part of the time and slower than
<m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m> part of the time. But it is reasonable to guess
that at some time between <m>t=a</m> and <m>t=b</m> your instantaneous velocity was
exactly <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>. The mean value theorem says that, under
reasonable assumptions about <m>f</m>, this is indeed the case.</p>

<theorem xml:id="thm_DIFFmvt"><title>The mean value theorem</title>
<statement><p>
Let <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> be real numbers with <m>a \lt b</m>. And let <m>f(x)</m> be a function so that
<ul>
<li> <m>f(x)</m> is continuous on the closed interval <m>a \leq x \leq b</m>, and
</li>
<li> <m>f(x)</m> is differentiable on the open interval <m>a  \lt  x  \lt  b</m>
</li>
</ul>
then there is a <m>c \in (a,b)</m>, such that
<md>
<mrow>
f'(c)&amp;=\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}
</mrow>
<intertext>which we can also express as</intertext><mrow>
  f(b)&amp;=f(a)+f'(c)(b-a).
</mrow>
</md>
</p></statement>
</theorem>


<p>Let us start to explore the mean value theorem <mdash/> which is very frequently known as the
MVT. A simple example to start:</p>

<example><title>Apply MVT to a polynomial</title>
<p>
Consider the polynomial <m>f(x)=3x^2-4x+2</m> on <m>[-1,1]</m>.
<ul>
<li> Since <m>f</m> is a polynomial it is continuous on the interval and also differentiable
on the interval. Hence we can apply the MVT.
</li>
<li> The MVT tells us that there is a point <m>c \in (-1,1)</m> so that
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(c) &amp;= \frac{f(1)-f(-1)}{1-(-1)} = \frac{1-9}{2} =-4
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
</ul>
This example is sufficiently simple that we can find the point <m>c</m> and the corresponding
tangent line:
<ul>
<li> The derivative is
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(x) &amp;= 6x-4
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> So we need to solve <m>f'(c)=-4</m>:
<md>
<mrow>
  6c-4 &amp;= -4
</mrow>
</md>
which tells us that <m>c=0</m>.
</li>
<li> The tangent line has slope <m>-4</m> and passes through <m>(0,f(0))=(0,2)</m>, and so is
given by
<md>
<mrow>
  y &amp;= -4x+2
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> The secant line joining <m>(-1,f(-1))=(-1,9)</m> to <m>(1,f(1))=(1,1)</m> is just
<md>
<mrow>
  y &amp;= 5-4x
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li><p> Here is a sketch of the curve and the two lines:</p>

<sidebyside width="75%">
<image><latex-image><![CDATA[
\begin{tikzpicture}
\begin{axis}[
  width=7cm,
  legend style={
    cells={anchor=east},
    legend pos=outer north east,
  },
  axis x line=center, axis y line=center,
  xmax=1.2,xmin=-1.2, xtick={-1,-0.5,0.5,1},
  ymin=-1, ymax=10,
  ytick={0,3,6,9},
  yticklabels={0,3,6,9}
  ]
\addplot[black,domain=-1.1:1.1,samples=100] {3*x*x-4*x+2}; \addlegendentry{$3x^2-4x+2$}
\addplot[blue,domain=-1.1:1.1,samples=100] {5-4*x};  \addlegendentry{$5-4x$}
\addplot[red,domain=-1.1:1.1,samples=100] {2-4*x};  \addlegendentry{$2-4x$}
\end{axis}
\end{tikzpicture}
]]></latex-image></image>
</sidebyside>
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</example>

<example><title>MVT, speed and distance</title>
<p>
We can return to our initial car-motivated examples. Say you are driving along a straight
road in a car that can go at most <m>80km/h</m>. How far can you go in 2 hours? <mdash/> the answer
is easy, but we can also solve this using MVT.
<ul>
<li> Let <m>s(t)</m> be the position of the car in <m>km</m> at time <m>t</m> measured in hours.
</li>
<li> Then <m>s(0)=0</m> and <m>s(2)=q</m>, where <m>q</m> is the quantity that we need to bound.
</li>
<li> We are told that <m>| s'(t) | \leq 80</m>, or equivalently
<md>
<mrow>
-80 \leq s'(t) \leq 80
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> By the MVT there is some <m>c</m> between 0 and 2 so that
<md>
<mrow>
  s'(c) &amp;= \frac{q-0}{2} = \frac{q}{2}
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> Now since <m>-80 \leq s'(c) \leq 80</m> we must have <m>-80 \leq q/2 \leq 80</m> and hence
<m>-160 \leq q=s(2) \leq 160</m>.
</li>
</ul>
</p></example>

<p> More generally if we have some information about the derivative, then we can use the
MVT to leverage this information to tell us something about the function.</p>

<example><title>Using MVT to bound a function</title>
<p>
Let <m>f(x)</m> be a differentiable function so that
<md>
<mrow>
  f(1)&amp;=10 &amp;\text{ and }&amp;&amp; -1 \leq f'(x) \leq 2 \text{ everywhere}
</mrow>
</md>
Obtain upper and lower bounds on <m>f(5)</m>.
</p>

<p>Okay <mdash/> what do we do?
<ul>
<li> Since <m>f(x)</m> is differentiable we can use the MVT.
</li>
<li> Say <m>f(5)=q</m>, then the MVT tells us that there is some <m>c</m> between <m>1</m> and <m>5</m> such
  that
<md>
<mrow>
 f'(c) &amp;=\frac{q-10}{5-1} = \frac{q-10}{4}
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> But we know that <m>-1 \leq f'(c) \leq 2</m>, so
<md>
<mrow>
-1 &amp;\leq f'(c) \leq 2
</mrow><mrow>
-1 &amp; \leq \frac{q-10}{4} \leq 2
</mrow><mrow>
  -4 &amp; \leq q-10 \leq 8
</mrow><mrow>
  6 \leq q \leq 18
</mrow>
</md>
</li>
<li> Thus we must have <m>6 \leq f(5) \leq 18</m>.
</li>
</ul>
</p></example>

</subsection>
<subsection><title>(Optional) <mdash/> Why is the MVT True</title>
<p>
We won't give a real proof for this theorem, but we'll look at a picture
which shows why it is true. Here is the picture. It contains a sketch of
the graph of <m>f(x)</m>, with <m>x</m> running from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m>, as well as
a line segment which is the secant of the graph from the point
<m>\big(a\,,f(a)\big)</m> to the point <m>\big(b\,,f(b)\big)</m>. The slope of
the secant is exactly <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>.</p>

<sidebyside width="60%">
<image source="text/figs/mvtc"/>
</sidebyside>

<p> Remember that we are looking for a point, <m>\big(c\,,f(c)\big)</m>, on the
graph of <m>f(x)</m> with the property that <m>f'(c)=\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>,
i.e. with the property that the slope of the tangent line at
<m>\big(c\,,f(c)\big)</m> is the same as the slope of the secant.
So imagine that you start moving the secant upward, carefully keeping
the moved line segment parallel to the secant. So the slope of the
moved line segment is always exactly  <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>.
When we first start moving the line segment it is not tangent to the curve <mdash/>
it crosses the curve. This is illustrated in the figure by the second line
segment from the bottom.
If we move the line segment too far it does not touch the curve at all.
This is illustrated in the figure by the top segment. But if we stop
moving the line segment just before it stops intersecting the curve at
all, we get exactly the tangent line to the curve at the point on the curve
that is farthest from the secant. This tangent line has exactly the desired
slope. This is illustrated in the figure by the third line
segment from the bottom.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="warning_mvt">
<title>Be Careful with Hypotheses</title>
<p>
The mean value theorem has hypotheses <mdash/> <m>f(x)</m> has to be continuous
for <m>a\le x\le b</m> and has to be differentiable for <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>.
If either hypothesis is violated, the conclusion of the mean value theorem
can fail. That is, the curve <m>y=f(x)</m> need not have a
tangent line at some <m>x=c</m> between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> whose slope, <m>f'(c)</m>,
is the same as the slope, <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>, of the secant joining
the points <m>\big(a\,,f(a)\big)</m> and <m>\big(b\,,f(b)\big)</m> on the
curve. If <m>f'(x)</m> fails to exist for even a single value of <m>x</m> between
<m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, all bets are off. The following two examples illustrate this.
</p>

<example xml:id="eg_mvtd"><title>MVT doesn't work here</title>
<p> For the first <q>bad</q> example, <m>a=0</m>, <m>b=2</m> and</p>

<sidebyside valign="middle">
<p><m>
f(x) = \begin{cases}
           0  &amp; \text{if }x \le 1 \\
           1 &amp; \text{if }x \gt 1
       \end{cases}
</m></p>
<image source="text/figs/mvtd"/>
</sidebyside>

<p>For this example, <m>f'(x)=0</m> at every <m>x</m> where it is defined. That is,
at every <m>x\ne 1</m>. But the slope of the secant joining
<m>\big(a\,,f(a)\big)=(0,0)</m> and <m>\big(b\,,f(b)\big)=(2,1)</m>
is <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.
</p></example>

<example xml:id="eg_mvte"><title>MVT doesn't work here either</title>
<p>For the second <q>bad</q>  example, <m>a=-1</m>, <m>b=1</m> and <m>f(x)=|x|</m>.
For this function</p>

<sidebyside valign="middle">
<p><m>
f'(x) = \begin{cases}
           -1  &amp; \text{if }x  \lt  0  \\
            \text{undefined} &amp; \text{if }x=0 \\
           1 &amp; \text{if }x \gt 0
       \end{cases}
</m></p>
<image source="text/figs/mvte"/>
</sidebyside>

<p>For this example, <m>f'(x)=\pm 1</m> at every <m>x</m> where it is defined. That is,
at every <m>x\ne 0</m>. But the slope of the secant joining
<m>\big(a\,,f(a)\big)=(-1,1)</m> and <m>\big(b\,,f(b)\big)=(1,1)</m>
is <m>0</m>.
</p></example>

<example xml:id="eg_mvtf"><title>MVT does work on this one</title>
<p>
Here is one <q>good</q> example, where the hypotheses of the mean value theorem
are satisfied. Let <m>f(x)=x^2</m>. Then <m>f'(x)=2x</m>. For any <m>a \lt b</m>,
<md>
<mrow>
\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}=\frac{b^2-a^2}{b-a}=b+a
</mrow>
</md>
So <m>f'(c)=2c</m> is exactly <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m> when <m>c=\frac{a+b}{2}</m>,
which, in this example, happens to be exactly half way between <m>x=a</m> and
<m>x=b</m>.</p>

<sidebyside width="50%">
<image source="text/figs/mvtf"/>
</sidebyside>

</example>

<p>A simple consequence of the mean value theorem is that if you know the
sign of <m>f'(c)</m> for all <m>c</m>'s between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, with <m>b \gt a</m>, then
<m>f(b)-f(a) = f'(c) (b-a)</m> must have the same sign.</p>

<corollary xml:id="cor_DIFFmvtcons"><title>Consequences of the mean value theorem</title>
<statement><p>
Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be real numbers with <m>A \lt B</m>.
Let function <m>f(x)</m> be defined and continuous on
the closed interval <m>A\le x\le B</m> and be differentiable on the
open interval <m>A \lt x \lt B</m>.
<ol label="a">
<li><p> If <m>f'(c)=0</m> for all <m>A \lt c \lt B</m>, then <m>f(b)=f(a)</m> for all
<m>A\le a \lt b\le B</m>.</p>
<p><mdash/> That is, <m>f(x)</m> is constant on <m>A\le x\le B</m>.</p>
</li>
<li><p> If <m>f'(c)\ge 0</m> for all <m>A \lt c \lt B</m>, then <m>f(b)\ge f(a)</m> for all
<m>A\le a\le b\le B</m>.</p>
<p>
<mdash/> That is, <m>f(x)</m> is increasing on <m>A\le x\le B</m>.</p>
</li>
<li><p> If <m>f'(c)\le 0</m> for all <m>A \lt c \lt B</m>, then <m>f(b)\le f(a)</m> for all
<m>A\le a \le b\le B</m>.</p>
<p><mdash/> That is, <m>f(x)</m> is decreasing on <m>A\le x\le B</m>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</p>

</statement>
</corollary>

<p> It is not hard to see why the above is true:
<ul>
<li> Say <m>f'(x)=0</m> at every point in the interval <m>[A,B]</m>. Now pick any <m>a,b \in [A,B]</m>
with <m>a \lt b</m>. Then the MVT tells us that there is <m>c \in (a,b)</m> so that
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(c) &amp;= \frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}
</mrow>
</md>
If <m>f(b) \neq f(a)</m> then we must have that <m>f'(c) \neq 0</m> <mdash/> contradicting what we are
told about <m>f'(x)</m>. Thus we must have that <m>f(b)=f(a)</m>.
</li>
<li> Similarly, say <m>f'(x) \geq 0</m> at every point in the interval <m>[A,B]</m>. Now pick any
<m>a,b \in [A,B]</m>  with <m>a \lt b</m>. Then the MVT tells us that there is <m>c \in (a,b)</m> so that
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(c) &amp;= \frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}
</mrow>
</md>
Since <m>b \gt a</m>, the denominator is positive. Now if <m>f(b)  \lt  f(a)</m> the numerator would be
negative, making the right-hand side negative, and contradicting what we are told about
<m>f'(x)</m>. Hence we must have <m>f(b) \ge f(a)</m>.
</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>A nice corollary of the above corollary is the following:</p>

<corollary xml:id="cor_equal_diff">
<statement><p>
If <m>f'(x) = g'(x)</m> for all <m>x</m> in the open interval <m>(a,b)</m>, then <m>f-g</m> is a constant on
<m>(a,b)</m>. That is <m>f(x)=g(x)+c</m>, where <m>c</m> is some constant.
</p></statement>
</corollary>

<p>We can prove this by setting <m>h(x)=f(x)-g(x)</m>. Then <m>h'(x)=0</m> and so the previous
corollary tells us that <m>h(x)</m> is constant.
</p>

<example><title>Summing <m>\arcsin</m> and <m>\arccos</m></title>
<p>
Using this corollary we can prove results like the following:
<md>
<mrow>
  \arcsin x + \arccos x &amp;= \frac{\pi}{2} &amp; \mbox{for all } -1  \lt  x  \lt  1
</mrow>
</md>
How does this work? Let <m>f(x) = \arcsin x + \arccos x</m>. Then
<md>
<mrow>
  f'(x) &amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} + \frac{-1}{\sqrt{1-x^2}} = 0
</mrow>
</md>
Thus <m>f</m> must be a constant. To find out which constant, we can just check its value at a
convenient point, like <m>x=0</m>.
<md>
<mrow>
  \arcsin(0) + \arccos(0) &amp;= \pi/2 + 0 = \pi/2
</mrow>
</md>
Since the function is constant, this must be the value.
</p></example>


</subsection>


<xi:include href="../problems/prob_s2.13.xml"/>

</section>
